Guide to the Stanford Family Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Family papers
1839-1964
SC0033D
Stanford family.
10 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Jane Lathrop Stanford, Thomas Welton Stanford, David Starr Jordan, Helen Stanford Canfield, David H. Canfield, and others; also includes purchases.
Information about Access
None.
Biography
The Stanford brothers were born in the township of Watervliet in upstate New York, the sons of Josiah and Elizabeth Stanford. Each of the brothers eventually went west to make his fortune. Josiah and Leland Stanford remained in California and became successful businessmen, and Thomas Welton Stanford continued on to a successful career in Australia.
Scope and Content
The Stanford family papers include letters, telegrams, newsclippings, photographs and photograph albums, genealogical notes, legal and financial papers, pamphlets, and printed materials of Josiah Stanford (1817-1890) and his wife Helen Allyne Barker Stanford (1831-1909), Josiah Winslow Stanford (1864-1937) and his wife Alice Herrick Stanford (1858-1940), Charles Stanford (1819-1885), Asa Philips Stanford (1821-1903), DeWitt Clinton Stanford (1826-1864), Thomas Welton Stanford (1832-1918), Welton Stanford (1849-1922), and Welton Stanford, Jr (1878-1947). The Thomas Welton Stanford series includes correspondence, photographs, transcripts of his Psychic Investigation Circle of Melbourne, Australia (10 volumes) and the "HARBINGER OF LIGHT" magazine (1906-1917). The collection also includes records of Warm Springs Ranch and the Warm Springs Hotel near San Jose, California.
Access Terms
Coover, Thomas Edgar.; Stanford Art Gallery..; Stanford family.; Stanford University. Department of Psychology.; Stanford University. Libraries.; Stanford, Alice Herrick,, 1858-1940.; Stanford, Asa Philips,, 1821-1903.; Stanford, Charles, 1819-1885.; Stanford, DeWitt Clinton, 1826-1864.; Stanford, Helen Allyne,, 1831-1909.; Stanford, Josiah Winslow, 1864-1937.; Stanford, Josiah, 1817-1890.; Stanford, Thomas Welton, 1832-1918.; Stanford, Welton, 1849-1922.; Stanford, Welton, 1878-1947.; Warm Springs Hotel (Calif.).; Warm Springs Ranch (Calif.).; Harbinger of Light.; Spiritualism.
Collection Contents
- Josiah Stanford [1817-1890] Papers, Series 1
  Josiah Stanford was one of Leland Stanford's older brothers. He moved to California in 1849 and started in business selling supplies to gold miners. He also had business interests in oil and wine growing on Warm Springs Ranch.
  - Biographical material, obituary (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Legal documents and bills, 1855-1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes deeds to property, last will and testament.
  - Correspondence relating to estate settlement, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Real estate abstracts of title, certificates of search, 1875-1885 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Helen M. Allyne Barker Stanford [1831-1909] Papers, Series 2
  Helen Stanford was the second wife of Josiah Stanford.
  - Legal documents and bills, and fourth account of her trust estate, 1890-1909, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Business book, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Lists daily chores for her kitchen help.
  - Personal mementos and letters, 1846 and undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photograph album of relatives and friends, including photo of Emmanuel Swedenborg (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Three small photograph albums of relatives and friends. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes photos of Leland and Jane L. Stanford; baby photos of Leland Stanford, Jr.; and daguerrotype of unidentified man and child, possibly Helen Stanford's first husband and daughter Gertrude.
- Allyne Family Papers, Series 3
  - Genealogy papers and clippings, 1863-1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes documents of Samuel H. Allyne, Helen's brother, murdered while with the Army in Texas, Dec. 29, 1863.
  - Samuel H. Allyne's wallet, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Josiah Winslow Stanford [1864-1937] Papers, Series 4
  Josiah W. Stanford was the son of Josiah and Helen Stanford. He ran the Warm Springs Ranch after his father's death, producing hay, barley and beef as well as wines.
  - Correspondence, 1897-1935 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes letter from Jane Stanford requesting his resignation as Stanford University trustee, and a copy of J. W.'s reply, 1898.
  - Mementos, clippings, and school maps, and 33 railroad passes, 1889-1927 and undated; 1881-1899 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, undated. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    School copybook; notebook; volume "A Legend of Warm Springs" with covering letter and poem "Joey on the Farm" by E. R. Taylor; and logbook of the yacht "Lotus."
  - Bills and legal documents, 1888-1900 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bills and legal documents, 1903-1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Expense ledger, 1898-1906 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - General account ledger, 1918-1924 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General account ledger, 1924-1927 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Account ledger of personal holdings (stocks, bonds, real estate, ranch account, schooner "Nicoline"), 1889-1913 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Alice Herrick Stanford [1858-1940] Papers, Series 5
  Alice Herrick Stanford was the second wife of Josiah Winslow Stanford.
  - Herrick genealogy, clippings, letters, mementos, 1877-1931 and undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Cookbook, n.d., and autograph album, 1875-1883 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Diaries (New Orleans trip), and (trip to Europe, with three photos), 1887, 1899 1913 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Diaries, 1901 and 1902 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Warm Springs Ranch Records, Series 6
  - Stanford family guest register, 1900-1909 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - List of cellar wines, and Peralta Ranch expense ledger, 1887-1893, 1890-1904 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Abstracts of title, 1869, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Account ledger, payment of workmen, 1884-1895 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Account ledger, payment of workmen, 1893-1915 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Legal documents and bills, 1860-1871 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Legal documents and bills, 1872-1884 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Bills and invoices, 1895-1909 and undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Holograph manuscript "Treatment of Stuck wines" by J. W. Stanford, Holograph MS, description of Warm Springs, and typed copy, Correspondence on proposed road, 1892 undated 1922 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Expense Ledger, 1870-1883 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous accounts and wine orders, 1870-1888 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous accounts and wine orders, 1888-1894 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Bills paid, 1888-1891
  - Miscellaneous accounts and wine orders, 1895-1910 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Warm Springs Hotel Records, Series 7
  - Expense and account ledger, 1863-1865 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Guest day book, 1865 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Bills for newspaper advertisements, 1863-1866 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Menus, wine lists, room rates, miscellaneous printed material, 1860s (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Private correspondence of William Redding, 1852-1865 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Redding was general manager of the hotel from 1863-1868. Letters are in Spanish and English, mainly from Redding's relatives in Mexico. Also included is one letter of Redding's on San Francisco paper, 1855.
  - Expense accounts, 1863-1864
  - Expense accounts, 1864-1868
  - Day book, 1865-1866
  - Day book, 1866-1867
- Charles Stanford [1819-1885] Papers, Series 8
  Charles Stanford was an older brother of Leland Stanford.
  - Assorted papers, 1839-1963 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Two letters, 1839, 1847. Money exchange, 1862. Two copies of In Memoriam Josiah Stanford (Charles' son Josiah who died in his teens). Correspondence relating to Charles with Gladys Wells Griffith, Charles' granddaughter, 1951-1963.
  - Scrapbook of clippings, obituaries, newspaper articles on the Stanford and Wells families, 1873-1896. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Probably compiled by Nora Stanford Wells, Charles' daughter. Includes newspaper columns by Nora Stanford signed "Western Traveller," describing a trip from New York to California in Leland Stanford's private railroad car, 1877. Scrapbook presented by Gladys Wells Griffith, Nora's daughter.
- Asa Phillips Stanford [1821-1903], Series 9
  Asa Phillips Stanford was an older brother of Leland Stanford.
  - Legal documents pertaining to Sisquoc Ranch, Santa Barbara County, 1851-1868 and undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Legal documents pertaining to San Vicente Rancho, Santa Cruz County, 1862-1865 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Assorted financial documents, 1853-1869 and undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Includes 8 stock certificates from "The Lady Bryan Golda and Silver Mining Co." and 6 stock certificates from the "Pick and Shovel Silver Mining Co."
  - Newspaper clipping about Asa Phillips after his death, 1903 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Dewitt Clinton Stanford [1826-1862] Papers., Series 10
  Dewitt Clinton Stanford, a younger brother of Leland Stanford, was a partner in some of the Stanford brothers' business ventures in California. He moved to Australia with his brother Thomas Welton Stanford in 1860, where he died in April 1862.
  - Eight letters, 1851-1862 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Includes description of ocean voyage to Australia with Thomas Welton Stanford, 1860.
- Stanford Family Miscellaneous Papers, Series 11
  - Two volumes used by Josiah Stanford on manufacture of oils: The Manufacture of Photogenic or Hydrocarbon Oils, and A Practical Treatise on Coal, Petroleum and Other Distilled Oils, 1859 1865 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Articles and correspondence re Stanford oil interests, 1935-1938 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous items, 1858-1962 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Four receipts for good shipped by Stanford Bros., 1858. Two articles about the Stanford family, 1862 (reproduced on silk) and 1866. Copy of newspaper article on locust Grove, Stanford home near Schenectady, New York, 1962.
  - Miscellaneous material on assorted (and usually distant) Stanford relatives and descendants, including Welton genealogy, newspaper clippings, and death notices, 1950 and undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Legal documents regarding assorted people, 1854-1901 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Thomas Welton Stanford [1832-1918] Papers, Series 12
  Thomas W. Stanford was the youngest of Leland Stanford's brothers. Like his brothers, he operated a store in the gold fields in California, but sold it after several years. He moved to Melbourne, Australia, and became a prosperous businessman there. In 1870 he founded the Victorian Association of Progressive Spiritualists and actively pursued his interests in spiritualism. He was a Trustee of Stanford University and an early benefactor of the University.
  - 24 letters to his family, circa 1851-1866 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Personal correspondence, 1893-1915 and undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Includes a copy of a letter to the Secretary, Parliamentary Commission on Decimal Coinage, regarding adoption of English half-sovereign as unit of decimal system of currency for Australia, 1901.
  - Article: Thomas Welton Stanford, a Brief Character Sketch, by L. M. Terman, from notes by J. E. Coover, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Clippings and listings of Thomas Welton's donations to Stanford University - paintings, apports, library fund. Copy of his will, 1914. Pamphlet about James W. Curtis, landscape artist. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Australiana in Leland Stanford Junior University Library, 1897 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Letters, interviews, articles about his life, death, and interests, 1918-1964 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Pamphlets, clippings, letters on spiritualism, psychic phenomena, 1903-1914 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Two issues of Fate magazine, with articles on Stanford University and psychic research, 1949, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of apports and other things conjured up, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript, "Experiments with the divining rod" by Vickery, Letters, notes on psychic phenomena by various people, 1914 1914 and undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Original wrapping paper of apports. Pieces of Australian newspaper. Miscellaneous notes and papers, 1902-1914 and undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of spirit pictures, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Lectures; Psychic Investigation at T. W. Stanford's Circle, Melbourne, 1902-03 (Box 10)
  - Lectures; Psychic Investigation at T. W. Stanford's Circle, Melbourne, 1905-06 (Box 10)
  - Lectures; Psychic Investigation at T. W. Stanford's Circle, Melbourne, 1907 (Box 10)
  - Lectures; Psychic Investigation at T. W. Stanford's Circle, Melbourne, 1907 (Box 11)
  - Lectures; Psychic Investigation at T. W. Stanford's Circle, Melbourne, 1909 (Box 11)
  - Lectures; Psychic Investigation at T. W. Stanford's Circle, Melbourne, 1910-11 (Box 11)
  - Lectures; Psychic Investigation at T. W. Stanford's Circle, Melbourne, Jan-Jun 1912 (Box 12)
  - Lectures; Psychic Investigation at T. W. Stanford's Circle, Melbourne, Jul-Dec 1912 (Box 12)
  - Lectures; Psychic Investigation at T. W. Stanford's Circle, Melbourne, Jan-Jun 1913 (Box 12)
  - Lectures; Psychic Investigation at T. W. Stanford's Circle, Melbourne, Jul-Dec 1913 (Box 12)
  - Harbinger of Light magazine, unbound copies, (missing May 1909), 1908-1911 (Box 13)
  - Harbinger of Light magazine, 1906-08
  - Harbinger of Light magazine, 1908
  - Harbinger of Light magazine, 1909
  - Harbinger of Light magazine, 1910
  - Harbinger of Light magazine, 1911
  - Harbinger of Light magazine, 1912-13
  - Harbinger of Light magazine, 1914-15
  - Harbinger of Light magazine, 1916-17
  - Australian clippings: scrapbook of clippings pertaining to T. W. Stanford's psychic activities and the visit of Admiral Sperry's fleet to Sydney, New South Wales, 1908 (Box 14)
- Welton Stanford Family, Series 13
  Welton Stanford [1849-1922] was Leland Stanford's nephew (the son of Charles Stanford). His son Welton Stanford, Jr., was born in 1878.
  - Scrapbook of Welton Stanford, Jr., pertaining to Stanford family estates, railroad affairs, and Jane L. Stanford; print of Welton Stanford, and photograph of family home "Locust Grove" in Schenectady, NY, 1885-1901, circa 1880 (Box 15 os)
  - Scrapbook of Welton Stanford, Jr., pertaining to Jane L. Stanford, railroad affairs, Stanford University, Leland Stanford estate settlement, and social affairs of Welton Stanford family; and photograph album of Welton Stanford, Jr., from a trip to Europe, 1894-1902, 1897 (Box 16 os)